Preliminary Guide to the Samuel Clark Harvey Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Samuel Clark Harvey papers
1796-1994
1907-1953
MS 1244
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11.25
Personal and professional papers of Samuel Clark Harvey.
Harvey, Samuel Clark, 1886-1953
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Historical Medical Library, 1980. Gift of Louise Guion and Elizabeth Harvey, 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series and one addition: I. Correspondence and Lectures. II. Research Materials. III. Writings. IV. Writings of Others and Miscellaneous. V. Papers Re: Books and Bibliography.
Biographical / Historical
Samuel C. Harvey (1886-1953): surgeon; Ph.B., Yale, 1907, M.D., 1911; instructor of surgery, Yale University, 1919-1921, associate professor, 1921-1924, William H. Carmalt professor of surgery, 1924-1947, professor of surgery (oncology), 1947-1952; retired and continued research in field.
Scope and Contents
Personal and professional papers of Samuel Clark Harvey.
Medicine -- Historiography; Medicine -- History; Surgery; Educators; Physicians; Harvey, Samuel Clark, 1886-1953; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. School of Medicine
- Correspondence and Lectures, 1917-1953; Series I
  - Katharine Kingsley (Farnam) Harvey (Mrs. S.C. Harvey): ALS to F. G. Kilgour re: S. C. Harvey's papers, 1953 November 3 (Box 1)
  - Personal correspondence, with miscellaneous notes, typescripts, printed matter, mostly re: history of medicine, 1917-1918, 1936-1951 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, A-R, 1932-1952 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and printed matter from medical associations
    - A, 1937-1953 (Box 1)
    - C-S, 1946-1953 (Box 2)
  - Hawaii Territorial Medical Association: 58th Annual Meeting, 1948 May: correspondence, typescripts of lectures, audio records, printed matter, 1946-1948 (Box 2)
- Research Materials, 1796-1953; Series II
  - "The Breaking Strength of Healing Fractured Fibulae of Rats," study by S. C. Harvey, R. M. McKeown, and others: notes, typescripts, x-rays, charts, printed matter, 1933, undated (Box 3)
  - Burn wound treatment, and general wound healing: correspondence, notes, MSS, typescripts, patient records, printed matter (including bulletins of the National Research Council, Subcommittee on Burns), 1944-1953, undated (Box 3)
  - Burn wound treatment, and general wound healing: correspondence, notes, MSS, typescripts, patient records, printed matter (including bulletins of the National Research Council, Subcommittee on Burns), 1944-1953, undated (Box 4)
  - Chlorophyll: correspondence, notes, typescripts, printed matter, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Contraceptives and cancer: correspondence, printed matter, 1947-1951 (Box 4)
  - History of Surgery: correspondence, notes, typescripts, printed matter, 1910-1932, undated (Box 4)
  - [History of Surgery?]: miscellaneous materials, including Harold S. Arnold's biographical materials on Bishop George Berkeley and Dr. William H. Carmalt; notes on influenza; and papers collected by S. C. Harvey, including printed by-laws of the Connecticut Medical Society, and one ALS each by Benjamin Silliman and Benjamin Silliman, Jr., 1796-1952 (Box 4)
  - Hospital care and insurance plans: correspondence, printed matter, 1932-1935 (Box 5)
  - Microscope slides, apparently re: skin of dogs and humans, 1950-1951 (Box 5)
- Writings, 1908-1952; Series III
  - S. C. Harvey bibliographies, undated (Box 6)
  - Bibliography on war medicine and surgery, undated (Box 6)
  - Case histories: typescripts, 1919-1920 (Box 6)
  - Writings: typescripts, reprints
    - 1908-1946 (Box 6)
    - 1942-1951 (Box 7)
    - 1952, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Illustrations for unidentified book, undated (Box 8)
- Writings of Others, and Miscellaneous, 1907-1960; Series IV
  - John Cecil Holm, "Golden Harvest": mimeographs of play, undated (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter by others, with S. C. Harvey's notes and correspondence, 1936-1952 (Box 9)
  - Yale 1907S, 1911M classbooks, correspondence, etc., 1907-1953 (Box 9)
  - Printed matter (especially obituaries) about S. C. Harvey and S. C. Harvey Memorial Scholarship, with photograph, 1953-1960 (Box 9)
- Papers Re: Books and Bibliography, 1929-1961; Series V
  - Departmental correspondence, and papers re: Historical Medical Library, 1929-1961 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous bibliographical notes, undated (Box 9)
  - Scrapbooks of publishers' advertisements re: historical medical books, undated (Box 9)
  - Bibliographical note cards, mostly re: history of medicine; possibly an inventory of Historical Medical Library, undated (Box 10)
- Additional Material, 1907-1994; Accession 2005-M-120
  - Correspondence
    - Harvey, Katharine Farnam [letters of condolence], 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Harvey, Samuel Clark, 1908-1937, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 3)
  - Personal papers
    - Harvey, Katharine Farman [includes family documents, memorabilia, printed matter], 1910-1962 (Box 1, Folder 4 - 11)
    - Harvey, Samuel Clark
      - Awards, degrees, and honors, 1910-1952 (Box 1, Folder 12 - 13)
      - Honorary and memorial publications, 1951-1994 (Box 2, Folder 14 - 16)
      - Writings by S. C. Harvey, 1941-1952 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Yale Medical School and related publications, 1954-1959, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Photographs
    - Harvey, Katharine Farnam, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Harvey, Samuel Clark, [1907, [1919?]-[1927], 1947-1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 20 - 21)
  - Oversize
    - Photographs, Circa 1948, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Scrapbook [World War I, American Expeditionary Forces, the Harvard unit organized by Harvey Cushing, M.D.], 1917-1919 (Box 3, Folder 22)